<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to the author of the late Letter out of the countrey, occasioned by a former Letter to a member of the House of Commons concerning the Bishops lately in the Tower, and now under suspension.</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65988</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12369033</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12369033</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60503</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65988)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 903:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to the author of the late Letter out of the countrey, occasioned by a former Letter to a member of the House of Commons concerning the Bishops lately in the Tower, and now under suspension.</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Wagstaffe. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691. --  Letter to a member of the House of Commons.</term>
               <term>Nonjurors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60503:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER To the Author of the late <hi>Letter out of the Countrey,</hi> occaſioned by a former <hi>Letter to a Member of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> concerning the Biſhops lately in the Tower, and now under Suſpenſion.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN a <hi>Peeviſh</hi> diſcourſe, I always expect to meet with more of Paſſion than Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And you have given me no ground to alter my opinion, I confeſs at the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, you make an Apology for your <hi>Peeviſhneſſes,</hi> but I think that does not mend the matter, it only ſhews that ſome men know their own infirmity, and yet cannot forbear to publiſh it to the world. And what allowances ſoever you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak and expect in a private correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and from your friend, yet there is not the ſame reaſon to expect it from the world; and to Print and Publiſh a <hi>peeviſh</hi> and fretful Letter, and then to cry out you <hi>were betray'd by ſickneſs,</hi> is a <hi>peeviſh,</hi> i.e. a ridiculous excuſe. For if you were <hi>diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd</hi> and <hi>peeviſh</hi> and knew it, why did not you ſtay till your thoughts were cooler? Wiſe men have always judged that grave and ſerious matters require a free and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate mind. And your Letter gives us an inſtance, that in a <hi>peeviſh</hi> fit, how much ſoever a man may be <hi>maſter of his Notions,</hi> he is not much maſter of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>I cannot be perſwaded, that you your ſelf believe, that qualms and indiſpoſitions are ſufficient Licences for Invectives, and that whenever your Head or Toe akes, you are thereby diſpenc'd with, to fall upon the Honour and Reputation of good and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Men? and therefore pardon me, if I think your <hi>peeviſhneſs</hi> hath ſome other cauſes beſides bodily temper. <hi>Envy</hi> is apt to raiſe the Spleen, and men of great Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and no great Virtue, are always jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of other mens merits. There was an honourable character, (and which they ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well deſerv'd) given of the Biſhops in the firſt Letter: And it is a Query (which you can ſatisfie) whether That was the ſole, or the concurring Cauſe, whether it made, or only contributed to your diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and meeting with prepar'd matter, and the humours on the fret, hath rais'd the ferment to that pitch of wrath and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which every where diſcovers it ſelf in your Letter.</p>
            <p>This is too invidious to be open and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd, and downright Detraction and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny melts away before the Reputations of ſuch Men, like Snow before the Sun. But to pretend mighty reſpects and eſteem, under that Vizor perhaps ſomething may be faſtned, however it muſt be own'd to be politickly done; obliquely to attack That Reputation, which can never without palpable infamy be directly attempted. You profeſs a <hi>particular veneration</hi> for theſe excellent Perſons, and not content with that you add, <hi>as true and great a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration as any body can pretend to.</hi> And I wonder how you would like to be thus reverenc'd your ſelf, to have ſuch good words made an inlet to defame you: a crafty artifice to cloud and eclipſe the glory of your Actions, and to leſſen (with all imaginable <hi>peeviſhneſs,</hi>) your juſt value and eſteem amongſt men, I fanſie, in ſuch a caſe you would be put hard to it to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt your Enemies, and your Admirers.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60503:2"/>
            <p> It is not very long ſince that <hi>theſe</hi> great and Reverend <hi>Prelates</hi> had ſignaliz'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by an unparallel'd act of Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, and for the Liberty and Property of the Subject, which the whole Nation beheld and admir'd, and gave publick demonſtrations of their Affection and Gratitude, ſuitable to ſo great and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable an occaſion: And now, out come you with your Letter, and (out of pure Veneration no doubt) do all you can to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preciate and undervalue the honour of it. Why. <hi>They did but their duty, and other men behaved themſelves as well as they.</hi> Such an ungenerous and impious ſcorn was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before put on ſo glorious an Action, and can proceed from nothing but a malice, or ingratitude, as unparallel'd as <hi>their</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. If theſe be the effects of <hi>Veneration,</hi> give me the man that ſpits in my face; I had rather be openly reproach'd, than to have the ſame thing done under fawning complements and hypocritical Reverences.</p>
            <p>You have got a fine expreſſion for this and call it, <hi>placing things in a true light;</hi> as if all the kingdom was blind before, in the unſiverſal applauſes and regards that were every where paid to <hi>them.</hi> And now forſooth they muſt recal their Praiſe and Thanks, and dance after your <hi>new light;</hi> which diſcovers that it was <hi>their indiſpenſable Duty, and the praiſe and thanks muſt be divided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was <hi>their indiſpenſable Duty,</hi> and they own it, but is it the worſe or the leſs for that? I fancy you would be glad, if you could prove it had not been their duty, for then you might have ſomething to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And is it not very commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and praiſe-worthy, for a man to do his duty? But how poor and thin (not to ſay baſe and unworthy) is your repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this great Action. As if they had perform'd only an eaſie and common duty, which notwithſtanding deſerves a better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, and treatment than you can afford to this high act of Religion, you tell us, <hi>you deſire to conſider the Actions in the</hi> naked <hi>Circumſtances.</hi> And I muſt tell you, that you conſider this Action very <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly</hi> indeed; for you omit the moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial and pertinent Circumſtances, which are the generous aſſerting of the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Liberties,</hi> to the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent hazard of themſelves, and all their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſts. You know theſe are Duties of great difficulty, and the performance of them hath been celebrated in all Ages of the Church. And when the Fathers of our Church have demonſtrated an invincible Zeal and Courage in aſſerting Religion, and the Laws: To have this repreſented with <hi>peeviſh</hi> and contemptible abatements, is a reproach to Chriſtianity, and reflects diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour upon the blood of Martyrs, and the faith and conſtancy of Confeſſors.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>You cannot ſee why they ſhould boaſt;</hi> and do they boaſt? of That all the world, and even your ſelf acquit them: but you would fain inſinuate it by proving from Scripture, they ought not to boaſt. 'Tis a Reflection upon humane Nature to anſwer ſuch inſinuations, and I appeal to the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of a <hi>Jew,</hi> for the iniquity of them. What tho' men cannot merit from God, muſt they not therefore have due praiſes from men? Envy and Detraction are no leſs Vices, and far more odious than Boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. S. <hi>Paul, That he might not be exalted was buffetted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</note> but it is to be remembred, that it was by a <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this rate, there will be no ſuch thing as Honour, Praiſe, and Reputation amongſt men, and the moſt renowned and illuſtrious Actions will ſhrink into a narrow compaſs; you may try it in any Action that from the beginning of the World, hath had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Great and Glorious; and it is lyable to the very ſame that you object to the Biſhops. Let us examine it in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of your own allowance. This very Action (provided the Biſhops may have as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60503:2"/>little the honour of it as may be) you are content to own that it was raviſhing and <hi>tranſporting,</hi> and that a <hi>whole Nation was never more oblig'd.</hi> Now, Sir, let there be as many ſharers in this as you pleaſe, and let all the ſhares be put together; let the <hi>Lords,</hi> the <hi>Lawyers</hi> and <hi>inferiour Clergy, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, defend</hi> and <hi>aſſiſt,</hi> as much as you ſhall think fit, the upſhot (in your way) will be no more honour, than you will allow to the Biſhops, a ſmall queſtion of yours will rifle it of all the glory you pretend to give it: For (as you ſay of the Biſhops) <hi>I would only ask this Queſtion, whether it was their duty or no?</hi> if it was, then <hi>without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the Popiſh doctrine of ſupererogation and merit, I cannot ſee why they ſhould boaſt, or we</hi> magnifie <hi>them ſo extremely for doing that which was their indiſpenſable duty.</hi> And ſo for any thing I can ſee, the Lords, the Lawyers, and the inferiour Clergy, (for all your <hi>extaſie</hi> and <hi>tranſport</hi>) muſt e'en go look for their honour, as well as the Biſhops, for as you have handled the matter, that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious action is come to a fair iſſue, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the foot of the account we have it, they did but their duty, and ſo <hi>need not have been ſo extremely magnify'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your pretending therefore to <hi>divide the thanks and praiſe,</hi> was not to give it to any body elſe, but to take it from the Biſhops. This is one of the crooked and ſerpentine ways of detraction, when the merit of an action cannot with any face be deny'd, then it deſerves not ſo much, or others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it too, you ſhould (you ſay) <hi>be unjuſt to others, if you ſhould ſuffer them to ingroſs all the praiſe.</hi> But what injuſtice is it to others to ſuffer the Biſhops to enjoy what is <hi>their</hi> due. It can never be deny'd but <hi>they</hi> had a ſhare in that action, and the greateſt ſhare too; There were others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in it, but that (tho' unawares to you) is ſo far from leſſening, that it is a conſiderable advance to the honour of theſe excellent Biſhops; for if the particular act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it deſerv'd praiſe and thanks, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſome part even of <hi>that</hi> praiſe and thanks is due to them who were the cauſe and occaſion of it; ſo that beſides the merit of their immediate and particular actings, (which was far the greateſt) there is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional honour due to <hi>them,</hi> from that which was effected by their Authority and example, by their wiſdom and conduct. For tho' (as you ſay) <hi>ſome of their inferiour Clergy, were as forward as themſelves,</hi> yet I muſt tell you (if you do not know it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready) they were but ſome, and thoſe (for the moſt part) the very ſame who ſtill in judgment and practice agree with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. To inſtance in one, the learned and fam'd Author of theſe admirable Reaſons, for <hi>not reading the Declaration, in a Letter from a Miniſter in the City, to one in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey:</hi> But there were others, and thoſe not inconſiderable, who at firſt, were not ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forward, ſome thought the reading the <hi>Declaration</hi> to be onely a MINISTERIAL ACT, and others but MATTER OF PRUDENCE, what Readineſs therefore they ſhew'd after, was not Original, but derivative, and is owing to the Influence and reaſons of the Biſhops, their <hi>ſeconding</hi> is to be aſcrib'd to the <hi>Principals,</hi> and they follow'd, but it was becauſe they had ſuch excellent <hi>Leaders.</hi> And for the truth of all this, I appeal to the tranſactions and debates at the ſeveral Conſultations which were held about this matter. Beſides, it ought not to be forgotten, that <hi>theſe Biſhops</hi> never tranſmitted the <hi>Declarations</hi> to their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Clergy, and each of them by that ſingle act ſecur'd a whole Dioceſſe. So that what ſhare ſoever others had in the action, no body can pretend to an equal ſhare in the Reputation. Had <hi>They</hi> comply'd, I doubt the Number of the <hi>Non-Readers</hi> would have been much inferiour to the <hi>Non-ſwearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know my Lords the Biſhops envy not man his ſhare and honour in that action,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60503:3"/>and would have been glad if there had been yet more concern'd in it. And there were ſome (you do not mention) who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding as well deſerve it, and had as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a part as thoſe you do mention; Thoſe are <hi>the Gentlemen of the Jury,</hi> who (to their immortal honour) brought in that juſt verdict, and tho' you have left them out (and perhaps becauſe they did ſo) their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and uprightneſs is celebrated by the preſent, and will be celebrated by ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ages. To give therefore the Biſhops their juſt honour, does not deprive that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Jury,</hi> nor any others concern'd of what is due to them, nor does the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the Lords and Lawyers reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Biſhops. They very well agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and what is given to one, is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from another, Partnerſhip in vertue is not ſubject to the rules of Arithmetick, to adjuſt the quota's and proportions of praiſe and thanks, they beſt ſubſiſt in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtock; 'Tis only your <hi>peeviſhneſs</hi> that talks of <hi>dividing.</hi> The action was united, and why not the honour? and thoſe that concurr'd in the action, will not be Rivals in the Glory.</p>
            <p>I am aſham'd to have ſaid thus much in ſo clear a matter, and I do heartily and humbly beg pardon of my Lords the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: To plead in ſuch a caſe is a kind of detraction, and to offer to wipe out ſtains, ſuppoſes a poſſibility of their ſticking. But I have this Apology, it is not ſo much the caſe of their Lordſhips, (for that I know to be above Calumny) but the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is concern'd, which hath already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven its judgment in univerſal approbation and applauſe, ſo that to reflect upon, or to diminiſh the Biſhops, is to diſparage the publick verdict, and is a Libel upon the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>Before I leave this, there is one thing more I ſhall acquaint you with, and that is, that how much fidelity, zeal, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſoever theſe excellent Biſhops have ſhewn in this particular it is not the onely inſtance they have done it in, <hi>Their</hi> vertues have been try'd before, there was a time when <hi>A ſolemn League and Covenant,</hi> and another, when an <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was to be taken, and then <hi>they</hi> gave admirable proofs of their Conſtancy, and even in their younger years ſhew'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be men of Epiſcopal vertues, that neither the Power nor peril of the times, nor the baits of intereſt, nor any ſecular matter could prevail upon their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor could they be any more perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſwallow the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> than they were to read the <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Sir, you are very pert about fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their places with as good and able men as they, I will not queſtion your ſtock, but if you will count again, I doubt (tho' it be but a ſmall number) you will be put to it, to find even <hi>four or five</hi> of ſuch try'd and experienc'd vertue, and who can come up to the pitch and meaſure of <hi>their</hi> Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Conſtancy.</p>
            <p>I come now to that you call <hi>a leſs plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Subject, their Refuſing the Oaths.</hi> I will not diſpute with you whether they have done well, or ill, or whether they ought, or ought not to take the Oaths. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have offer'd any thing conſiderable to convince them.</p>
            <p>You ſay <hi>you will be ſo kind to them, as to make them Judges in their own cauſes.</hi> Well that is a kindneſs, and in conſequence of it, I pray let their Lordſhips be ask'd, and the matter, I ſuppoſe, will ſoon be at an end. But you do not mean ſo, onely a Paper they ſet their hands to almoſt a Twelve-month ſince. If all the <hi>Declarations</hi> that men have ſubſcribed muſt be their <hi>Judges,</hi> (however the Biſhops may eſcape,) I am afraid, thoſe that are ſo hot upon this, would not be able to ſtand the Trial themſelves of their own <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions.</hi> And yet there is a very great difference between thoſe <hi>Subſcriptions,</hi> and this of the Biſhops,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60503:3"/>and the other Lords. When that <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at <hi>Guild-hall</hi> was made and ſubſcrib'd, <hi>The times were in the utmoſt confuſion, the King was withdrawn, the Rabble up in all parts of the Kingdom, the Neceſſities preſſing and urgent:</hi> put all theſe together, and if there had been any need, there is reaſon and ground enough for allowances; and however it is very unſeaſonably urged by thoſe, who themſelves are ſo little ty'd to their own <hi>ſolemn</hi> and <hi>deliberate Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I pray what is there in This DECLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION that ſo warmly affects the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as that they ſhould refuſe to be judg'd by it. The ſhort of it is, <hi>That they reſolv'd to apply themſelves to the P. of</hi> O, <hi>who had undertaken</hi> (and promis'd by HIS DECLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION) <hi>to reſcue us, by endeavouring to procure</hi> A FREE PARLIAMENT: <hi>That they would aſſiſt him in the obtaining ſuch a</hi> Parliament, <hi>wherein our Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may be ſecur'd, the Proteſtant intereſt ſupported, to the glory of God, the happineſs of the <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> Government of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</hi> And now Sir, I pray tell me, what contradiction is there in all this, to their preſent or to their former practiſes. Was it that they declared to endeavour for a <hi>Free Parliament?</hi> That very thing, <hi>THEY</hi> had done in their <hi>Advices and Petition not long before.</hi> Or was it that they applyed to the P. of <hi>O.</hi> and promiſed to aſſiſt him? Why they promis'd to aſſiſt him but in the obtaining a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> as might ſecure the Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the glory of God, and the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> Government. And what is all this to Swearing? how comes there to be ſuch an inſeparable connexion between the <hi>Oath</hi> and the <hi>Declaration?</hi> that the refuſing the one is a palpable vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the other. Cannot a man endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> and promiſe to aſſiſt the P. of <hi>O.</hi> in procuring one, but that in his <hi>own judgment</hi> he muſt think himſelf obliged to take the Oath, and if he does not, he recals his conſent, and flyes from his ſubſcriptions? How you will prove this, I cannot tell; and I am confident from theſe Premiſſes all the skill you have, can never draw ſuch a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>The next thing you proceed upon is, That <hi>Salus populi eſt ſuprema lex:</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Maxim, you ſay, <hi>you will diſpute the matter in cool bloud.</hi> I am glad of that, for hitherto your bloud or your choler has been very hot: And (to do you right) what follows is the <hi>cooleſt</hi> thing you have ſaid in all your Letter. You ſay, <hi>The ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is deriv'd from the</hi> old Romans, <hi>among whom the People with the Senate, had the face of the ſupreme Magiſtracy. So that in our Conſtitution, the King is concern'd in that Maxim, and is not to be ſhut out from his ſhare in it.</hi> Very well, Sir, hitherto 'tis very <hi>cool. But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>in admitting a head, I would not exclude the Body.</hi> And ſo ſay I too, and (if you pleaſe) add, that in admitting a Body, you would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Head: and then it is as broad as long. You proceed with your Argument, <hi>Altho' 'tis poſſible Kingdoms may have ſuffer'd by the Peoples encroachments, yet to ſay, that a Government can ſuffer in no other inſtance, would be full as abſurd, as to ſay, That a man can be mortally wounded no where but in his head; but we are ſure there are parts in our body as fatal to be touch'd as the Brain, and therefore ought to be guarded with equal care.</hi> That is, if the Mouth bites the finger the Teeth are to be pull'd out, if the Head ſends defluxions upon the Lungs, the Head muſt be cut off; becauſe the Lungs are a Vital part, and ought to be guarded with equal care. Sir, It is to be hop'd after ſuch clear Demonſtrations, that now my Lords the Biſhops will be convinc'd and take the Oath.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>In thoſe caſes we are not ty'd up to the rigor and words of a Law: for if the moral Equity and the deſign of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60503:4"/>is better obſerv'd by breaking the Letter, 'tis lawful, nay our duty to do it;</hi> and to make good this, you inſtance in the Sabbath, and the <hi>Maccabees</hi> breaking the letter of the fourth Commandment: in which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, the Rule holds good; as alſo in all Ceremonial and poſitive Inſtitutions. But how comes this Rule to be extended to Moral Laws? The moral Equity of the fourth Commandment, we know; but I pray, which is the <hi>moral Equity of the fifth Commandment?</hi> or of any other <hi>Moral</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, upon the account of which a man may break the Letter and act contrary to it, and yet keep the Commandment? when you ſpeak plain to this, you will find your Account will reach all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as well as the <hi>Fifth;</hi> and in vertue of it, a man may be permitted to take <hi>God's name in vain,</hi> to commit <hi>Murder, Theft,</hi> or bear <hi>falſe witneſs</hi> as well as <hi>not honour his Father and Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are a little pleaſant, when you talk of being <hi>wiſe Martyrs</hi> to the <hi>Fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi> But by this you do not only ridicule <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> but alſo all the Martyrs and Sufferers for Religion in the Primitive Perſecutions; for they were juſt ſuch <hi>wiſe Martyrs</hi> and no other. For the Rule of breaking the Letter of a Law by the <hi>Moral Equity</hi> of it, is ſure full as early, and would ſerve them as well as any body elſe? And theſe inſtances of <hi>Equity</hi> you mention, <hi>That Kings were made for the people, not the people for Kings; that the Rights of the Subject ought to be as Sacred as thoſe of the Soveraign. That Government was not erected for the aggrandiſing one ſingle perſon or family.</hi> All theſe were the very ſame in thoſe days, as they are now. And I challenge you to name one ſingle inſtance of <hi>Moral Equity</hi> which did not equally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect them, as any Perſons ſince, and might not have been as ſerviceable to them. And therefore ('till you can ſhew the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) They will be even juſt ſuch <hi>wiſe Martyrs,</hi> ignorant of <hi>Moral Equity,</hi> and the advantages they might have had by that, to releaſe themſelves <hi>from the rigor and words of a Law.</hi> Of all the men I ever met with, you have a peculiar Talent in vilifying the greateſt and moſt honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Actions. And my Lords the Biſhops have reaſon to take it kindly, for you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that they did their duty, and that is more than you will allow the <hi>Martyrs.</hi> For (ſays your Rule) <hi>if the Moral Equity</hi> (and which was the ſame to the Martyrs as to any ſince) <hi>is better obſerv'd by break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Letter, 'tis lawful, nay</hi> our Duty <hi>to do it:</hi> and then the ſuffering Martyrs, either did not underſtand, or elſe neglected <hi>their Duty</hi> when they poſſeſſed their Souls in Patience, and choſe rather to ſuffer than (by Virtue of a <hi>Moral Equity</hi>) to break the Letter of God's or man's Law. Your friend, Mr. <hi>Johnſon,</hi> (who loves <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience</hi> as little as you do) can tell you,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw. to Jovian. p.</hi> 160.</note> that the Primitive Chriſtians ſuffered patiently becauſe the Laws were againſt them, <hi>i.e.</hi> the Letter of the Laws. For <hi>Moral Equity</hi> was as much on their ſide before, as after the Laws were made in their behalf. That indeed gave them a Title to the Letter, but they had before the Equity.</p>
            <p>I have now done with your Arguments: A Province I had much rather be imployed in, than in conſidering Reproaches and Scandals, but that cannot be avoided in your Letter. For after <hi>you have ſaid all you can to convince them;</hi> the next thing is to ſay all you can to defame <hi>them.</hi> And I defie any man to ſay more, or with Truth and Honeſty half ſo much.</p>
            <p>You have the ſtrange confidence to charge theſe Reverend and Excellent Biſhops with <hi>having been the occaſion of the expence of ſo much Treaſure and Blood.</hi> And you inſtance in <hi>Ireland.</hi> This is a very heavy charge, but it is as ridiculous as it is ſcandalous. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60503:4"/>(when your hand was in) that you did not charge them for having been the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all that mortality in the Navy the laſt Summer, or that the <hi>Pendennis</hi> was caſt away, or (to come a little nearer the matter, and becauſe you talk of <hi>Ireland</hi>) that they were the occaſion of an <hi>unfortunate Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's drowning himſelf.</hi> All this you might have charged upon them, and a great deal more, and with the ſame truth and juſtice.</p>
            <p>You have forgot what you ſaid a little before, <hi>That they had no Partners, no body pretends to ſhare with them, and they muſt ſtand or fall by themſelves:</hi> and how does this account, and the preſent charge agree? Can men that are ſo few and inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble do ſuch mighty things, as to ſtop Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and prevent the relief of <hi>Ireland.</hi> A man would be tempted to call theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, but perhaps you that can joyn <hi>veneration</hi> and <hi>reviling,</hi> may reconcile it: in the mean time, I pray Sir, Did they hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the City from lending Moneys on that occaſion, or did they hinder the raiſing of Men, or was they any impediment to the Parliament to promiſe aſſiſtance for the Reduction of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or finally, did they hinder the Wind and Tides. Sir, the Houſe of Commons is now inquiring into the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages concerning <hi>Ireland,</hi> and if you have any thing to ſay againſt the Biſhops, it is very proper to apply your ſelf to the Committee, and they have voted you ſhall have liberty of acceſs, and be heard. But if you can ſay no more than you do in your Letter, give me leave to tell you. It is a high act of villany to charge any Man, and eſpecially Men of their ſtation, honour, and worth, with having been the occaſion of ſpilling Proteſtant blood, and yet have not one wiſe word to ſay in proof of it.</p>
            <p>And what is this to their refuſing the Oath which was not 'till after the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> were come over, and <hi>Derry</hi> was beſieged, and reliev'd? I do not know what placing things in a true light may do, but in the old way of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, the occaſion cannot be after the fact: And I deſire you would pleaſe to ſhew how the Biſhops refuſing the Oath in <hi>July,</hi> was the occaſion that Succors were not ſent to <hi>Ireland</hi> the <hi>February</hi> or <hi>March</hi> before.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, I ſhall addreſs my ſelf to you, upon the end and deſign of the firſt Letter, which is to recommend to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament the mitigating or releaſing the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of the Oath Act, in favour of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Biſhops. This you ſay you muſt approve of, and for the truth of it, appeal to your Correſpondent. But you do not approve of the method propoſed. Well Sir, Methods are not much to me. And if your method is better, you ſhall have my vote, if you pleaſe, we will compare them. The firſt Letter (in purſuit of this end) recommends them as Men <hi>who are the chief for merits, as well as Authority in our Church. That their unparallet'd zeal for the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, and for the priviledges and liberty of the ſubject, deſerv'd another kind of acknowledgment and return from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That the zeal and courage they made appear, cannot be ſo ſoon forgot. That it would be a wonder and aſtoniſhment that theſe Prelates who had eſcaped the fury of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and made ſo glorious a confeſſion for Proteſtant Religion and Engliſh Liberties, ſhould in ſo ſhort a time be diſgrac'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by Proteſtants, and when others that attempted to enſlave the Nation, and even the Proſecutors of the Biſhops are received into favour; The chief Champions of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion and Liberty, are the onely men that are ruin'd,</hi> &amp;c. Sir, in my judgment, this is a pretty good method; and now if you pleaſe, let us ſee what yours is. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of this, you tell us <hi>they did but their duty, and need not be ſo extremely magnified, that they are men of ſuch a temper, that neither God nor man can do any thing for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60503:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>them; you</hi> charge them <hi>with faction and ſchiſm, with the blood of</hi> Ireland, <hi>with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring their humour before ſerving God;</hi> and to carry the matter home, you tell us, that <hi>the People would not be concerned for</hi> their <hi>Deprivation,</hi> and <hi>there are many others as good as they to fill their places.</hi> Now Sir, what your end is in this you beſt know, but if it be to procure favour to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, you have taken the ſtrangeſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod that ever was heard on. Suppoſe a friend of yours ſhould undertake to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend you to the favour of a third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and in order to it, ſhould mention your uſefulneſs, and vertues, and former ſervices, (which in your own caſe, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you would think might be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tempting you to boaſt) Suppoſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pretending the ſame, ſhould ſay, I approve the deſign; and of any thing that ſounds in his favour, but I do not like the Method; For, Sir, This man did but his duty, he need not be ſo magnified, nor was he ſingular in thoſe ſervices, and not content thus to diminiſh you, ſhould vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie, aſperſe, and bely you beſides, I pray, when there is another <hi>true light</hi> to be put out, give me your opinion, what you would think of ſuch an advocate, or of his method.</p>
            <p>There is one thing more you and the Author differ upon in point of Method. The Author recommends it to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thus far you ſeem to like it well enough, but you would have the Biſhops firſt petition. Now Sir, I am not Critic enough in theſe matters, to know which is beſt: But this I know, that favours, the more free and unconſtrain'd they are, are always the greater and more generous, and (if I miſtake not) the favours to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and to the <hi>Quakers,</hi> were enacted and made into a Law, without any previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Petition from either of them. And why favours ſhould come harder to thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (and to ſuch eminent Lights of that Church) as I do not undertake to determine, ſo I leave it to them whoſe immediate concern it is to conſider. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
